Software engineering radio episode 41
architecture part four.
Welcome to another episode of software
engineering radio. This is episode
number four of not my actually episode
number four. It's the fourth in our
software architecture series of episodes
and it's probably also the last one with
the title software architecture. We'll
have related topics of course in the
future, but this is anyway this is
number four.
It's about architectural styles and
patterns and it's again Michael and
myself.
And so Michael, I think you like to
start explaining what architectural
styles and patterns actually are.
Yes and I I like to begin with uh
describing the situation where we are
currently. We assume that you have
you assigned your responsibilities, that
you have found the responsibilities of
your system
to fulfill your functional requirements,
your your features for example by using
CRC cards and um
you
now have basically a a domain model of
your system. You know the dependencies,
you have the responsibilities described
and now you have a set of non-functional
requirements, you have constraints, you
might have already some technology
decisions and you have technology
constraints. And now you need to find a
suitable I I call it
technical architecture
in that you insert your functional
architecture, that you remodel your
functional architecture,
um
compose it, partition it
into the technical architecture. And
here you need to find
suitable structures. And structures
the proven best practices here are very
often described as patterns. So we will
also describe general techniques and
concepts beyond patterns.
So historically I think it was like
that. So some people started to identify
architectural styles. I think this were
the SEI folks.
And then a subset of these styles have
been re- redescribed or reformulated as
patterns in POSA 1.
And therefore we have both both terms
architectural style and architectural
pattern.
So so if I got it right what you just
said then an architectural pattern
is kind of something you apply to a set
of domain objects in your domain model
in order to kind of weld it into a form
so that it can
realize your non-functional
requirements.
To to basically realize the the
dependencies, the interactions between
the domain objects that you
just identified. And
in your domain model they have a
straight relationship. They need to
interact in some means. And now you
define the means by which they interact.
Right. So an architectural style
therefore and also an architectural
pattern is then a proven way to build a
system.
Specifically a proven way to realize
certain non-functional requirements.
You'll you'll see during
the the episode that a certain
architectural style, just like in
building architecture, has certain
characteristics. So you can recognize a
certain architectural style or pattern
if you look into a system and analyze
it.
And therefore an architectural style can
also can also serve as a template to
some extent or a guide set of guidelines
to guide the design of your
architecture. Once you decided to use a
certain style,
a couple of consequences arise and that
tell you basically how you should
implement your system.
And as usual with patterns,
architectural patterns and styles can
help you document
your architecture because if I go to
Michael and say, "Hey, I've used the
pipes and filters architecture." then he
will know what I was talking about.
Yes, if you then add for what which
responsibility, how how did how did you
decompose your system, how did you apply
the pipes and filters, then I it's
crystal clear how the system will look
like. I I I have a clear view.
I can imagine how the system looks like
that he's talking about.
Right. Typically, an architectural style
is is made of
is made up of a set of
building blocks, component types,
artifacts, kinds of things,
as well as their relationship and their
connections. So, for example, just to to
peek into what we're going to talk about
the pipes and filters
architectural patterns, you have
filters that are certain types of
components that can manipulate data and
they're connected using pipes, which is
basically a transport between adjacent
filters. And also an architectural style
typically says something about
constraints
with regards to how you can combine the
things that make up the pattern. So, to
some extent, just to connect this to
some other topics,
to some extent this also it's almost
like a meta model. It it basically
defines things and you can apply this to
your
to your own environment or to your own
requirements. And actually, just to to
connect this,
if you work in model driven development,
you will often use architectural
patterns as starting point for your own
meta models.
They haven't been traditionally been
formalized into meta models, but the
message is somewhat related.
And an architectural pattern
differentiates itself from a design
pattern by the level of abstraction that
it focuses on. So, an architectural
style or architectural pattern has a
stronger impact, has a I would say
global impact on the architecture,
whereas a design pattern has a pretty
localized impact on the design.
Some people distinguish between
strategic aspects of a system, which are
the architectural patterns, and tactical
aspects of an implementation, which
would be the design patterns.
Yeah, and
I like those names.
And POSA 1 focuses specifically on those
architectural patterns, whereas, for
example, the GoF book focuses
specifically on design patterns.
Right. In this episode, we'll take a
look at certain well-known architectural
patterns,
basically those that are described in
POSA 1.
So, if you read POSA 1, you can you can
stop listening.
Um so, but before we do that,
we'd like to at least hint at a number
of other styles that have been described
in various forms. So, we'll briefly go
through these
styles, and then we'll elaborate on some
of them, specifically those that have
been designed described in POSA 1.
So, there are various high-level ways of
building systems. One is um the idea of
having independent parts that are
connected somehow. The other one is
basically to describe a data flow
through a system. You have systems that
are data-centered, where you describe
data structures and work on them. Then
you have the ideas of virtual the idea
of virtual machines. And finally,
basically a metaphor called call and
return, where you basically invoke
procedures.
And below the independent parts
category, you can first of all have a
set of communicating processes using
some kind of remote procedure call. You
can have event or message-based systems,
whereas the they are Yeah, they are
typically asynchronous. And between
under the communicating processes, you
can often
arrange things like plugins or
component-based systems. And as I said,
we're not going to go into details for
all of those.
In data flow systems, you can
distinguish between batch or sequential
systems.
Yeah, you all know them.
Pipes and filters, which we'll describe
later. And workflow systems, where we
explicitly describe workflow
and then execute actions as part of this
workflow.
In the data-centered
design or architectural area, you either
have typically a repository of data on
which different applications work. And
if you add some AI magic to it, this
basically becomes a blackboard. Some
people or many people say that
repository and blackboard is basically
the same.
Um in the virtual machine area, you can
either build interpreters that
interpret basically your your script or
your program. You can have rule-based
systems. And also, you can have
microkernels, which is somewhat
different, but also very important for
complex systems that need to be portable
over different operating systems or
different hardware.
Finally, in the call and return
domain,
you will typically find procedural
systems, object-oriented systems, and
also layers. Whereas
layers are somewhat different than the
other two paradigms. Procedural and
object-oriented are typically something
you find on programming language level.
Whereas the layers pattern is really a
pattern that you have to consciously
implement.
And then finally, there are two other
techniques, which is frameworks and
reflection.
Um they're kind of unrelated. They can't
easily be organized under one of the
headings we talked about. Um and for
frameworks and for reflections, we will
have separate episodes sometime in the
future.
So,
starting there, we'll now discuss some
of the more important architectural
patterns and we'll start with layers.
The layers pattern is typically used
pretty early in the architecting phase
when when splitting the
responsibilities.
Um,
it's advisable for many reasons that I
come back to
to split the the responsibilities
into layers and then group associated
responsibilities
at the same level of abstraction
typically
into
layers.
Popular examples are for example the
three-tier architectures where you
separated the persistence, the data
store from the actual business logic,
from the presentation. And then of
course, you can
grow on with go on with that and say,
well, we have a three, four, five,
six-tier architecture where we just then
separated out certain responsibilities
into an individual layer. And one of the
key properties of the layer, one of the
key constraints that layers architecture
imposes that you're only supposed to
invoke the next layer and top-down.
There is some exception that you might
do
hop one or two layers down for
performance optimization reasons.
to go down.
Only allowed to go down, right.
And in in the pure form, it's only going
one level down and call and definitely
not going up. And in the kind of relaxed
form, you can also go one or two layers
down for optimization reasons. But
in my experience, I always had to pay
the price later at at maintainability
when when changing or extend extending
the system.
So, just to add another example is of
course the TCP IP stack where you have
those nicely defined I think seven
layers just in the OC ISO OC OSI
whatever
networking protocol stack.
Yeah, the the consequences of that is of
course that you
um she it's it's kind of information
hiding principle that you shield
um
upper layers from the details from the
implementation details of lower layers.
And with that of course you get a better
reuse, you get better maintainability.
Um you minimize the dependencies
typically.
Yeah, because you can you only depend on
the level directly below you and
everything below that is hidden.
As a consequence uh and as a liability
um you have reduced efficiency because
you might have two or three hops
involved
if you don't do the optimization, if you
don't do relax the the constraints.
Another liability is that when whenever
you change something in your system you
have a cascades of of changes that
propagate through your system
when you touch the presentation layer
which requires uh some some kind of data
and you change the data then you change
have to change also the business logic
because that also touches the data and
then so um
extending for example your system in the
address field with a new property
um has a cascading uh changes.
down through all the layers.
Triggers down, yeah.
Yeah.
Can be annoying. But nonetheless, I
think we we discussed this when
preparing this episode. Um this is maybe
maybe the single most important
architectural pattern because it it's
really uh I mean a system where you
can't identify layers
is probably probably bad design. Not
always, but it's really an important
metrics.
The next pattern we'd like to talk about
is pipes and filters. And um
the idea is that you structure systems
that you want to provide a structure for
systems that process some kind of data
stream. Uh an example from one of my
customers uh the European Southern
Observatory, they're building radio
telescopes. So, they receive um
basically
radio signals from one or many of their
radio dishes and they have to filter it,
they have to process it, they have to do
all kinds of Fourier transformations and
all that kind of weird stuff that nobody
really understands, at least not from
the IT folks. You have to be
uh
astronomy guy. Anyway, so um the idea is
that what you do is you have a set of
filters and a filter basically receives
data at the left side, does something
with it, and pumps it out on the right
side. And um if you want to build um a
complex, for example, image
transformation or filtering system, then
you can build a chain of
filters which are connected by pipes.
So, pipes basically receive the data
from one from the outs- outgoing side of
of of uh the left-hand filter and then
transport it over to the following to
the upcoming filter. And of course, if
the system, for example, plays
asynchronous in that um
one filter might produce data faster
than the other one can consume it, then
it's um the job of the pipe to to queue
the data and and make sure that
everybody uh can work at their own pace.
Um
A couple of other known uses uh are
compilers, for example. A compiler is
often also some kind of pipes and
filters design, although it's not always
that explicit where
um
the data is uh the the the the program
is first parsed, then it's analyzed,
then the abstract syntax syntax tree is
built, then you do some kind of error
checking, then you create some kind of
intermediate representation, you
optimize on that one, and then you
create the back end code. So, that's
also a very typical pipes and filters
design. Another very well-known pipes
and filters filters application is the
Unix shell, where the term pipe, you
know, the the vertical bar, is actually
literally used to connect various
command line applications.
So, let's look at some of the
consequences. Um
Of course, the primary idea of this
pattern is that you can reuse the filter
components and build different filter
chains by just recombining existing
filters through
pipes, then of course.
You can then also
the idea of having pipes
queue data if one is faster than the
other one. Um if the the previous um
filter produces faster data faster than
the subsequent one can consume it. Um
so, you can isolate the queuing aspect
into the filters, I just Sorry, into the
pipes. Also, if you if you want, you can
even use parallel parallelism
here. So, if if you have very slow
filters because they do a very powerful
transformation, then you can have
several of them in parallel
um working on the data, assuming the
data or the problem can be parallelized.
So, you can work independent on in
different regions. That's not always the
case.
What are some of the negative
consequences?
First of all, and and that's probably
the most important one. Um
if you have if you have two
um
filters where filter one produces data
that filter two uh wants to
consume, then the data that is exchanged
has to be known or the data structure
has to be known to both of them. So, you
tie them together
basically by having common data
structures which the one side produces
and the other one consumes. So, you have
to agree on a data structure. And that's
of course a problem because it as I said
it it ties together otherwise
independent filters. And to avoid that
problem, you can of course have the
pipes do some kind of data
transformation. So, you have some kind
of transformation logic in the pipes so
that you uh have or that that the
filters themselves are independent. Of
course, then you have the overhead of
doing the transformation in the in the
pipes which is also a problem. Another
thing that has to be considered is error
handling because if you have an error in
for example filter number five,
um there is no there's not necessarily
any way how the previous filters can be
notified because they might already have
finished. So, since this is inherently
synchronous, you need some kind of way
to handle errors by some notification or
logging or callback or whatever. So,
this can also be a bit intricate.
Nonetheless, uh pipes and filters are
something that's also very widely used
and really very fundamental and
important architectural pattern.
Uh the next pattern is the the
blackboard pattern. And in that pattern,
um you
basically throw all the the data that
you have on the blackboard and you have
specialized uh workers
um that operate on that uh common set of
data.
And in the original documentation by
Poza, one, it it went into the
direction of artificial intelligence of
of having
um
partitioned responsibilities that
magically work together and produce an
end result. Um
In daily uh practice, um, I would call
it more of a, uh, shared repository. And
so, I see, um, the those two concepts
very related and and shared repository
actually the one who's more widely used,
uh, today. That you, um, very often even
persisted, uh, the the data in a, um, in
a central database. And you have some,
uh, front ends that just collect and
gather the data. And you have some back
ends that process on the data, um, time
independent or just decoupled, uh, from
the, uh, the original,
um, front end, um, services.
So, so traditionally, this pattern has
been used in expert systems where the
idea was that, you know, if you don't
have if if you want to optimize the
algorithm with which the expert system
finds a solution to a problem, you just
add additional workers
that pick up data that's in certain
states as you learn how to solve the
problem. So, you know, you could you
could add additional, um,
problem-solving agents to your overall
architecture without changing the
system's, but, you know, fundamentals.
You could easily add additional building
blocks or additional additional logic.
Yeah, and, um, one of the common
situations where you would apply such
an, uh, shared repository, um, design
would be, um, when you have, uh, for
example, some real-time processing going
on that captures the data and shouldn't
be influenced and and impacted by any
batch processing, uh, running in in the
background, maybe at nightly,
uh, runs or, uh, just who which can,
run independently, uh, of it. And so,
similar to the, uh, pipes and filters
pattern, you could you can decouple
responsibilities. You can have
parallelism, you can have multiple
workers working on the same data. Um,
and whereas in the pipes and filters uh
pattern, you had them working on
different sets of data. So, the dis-
data was disjoint. And um, here in the
the blackboard in the shared repository
pattern, they work actually on the same
data items. Of course, uh you then
easily come into the the problem of uh
synchronizing the the results of
transactions and and all those uh
nightmares.
Also, this is really an interesting
point because um there has been a system
called Linda
um by David Gelernter. Don't know what
kind of nationality is, I don't know how
to pronounce his name. Um, and and he
also used this repository approach, but
not for this expert system in AI AI kind
of stuff, but rather to build
distributed concurrent systems because
um he only provided a limited number of
primitive operations with which the
agents could access the repository.
Things like uh take and put and check
whether it's there and then take. You
know, those like atomic operations on a
shared repository just like on shared
memory. And he showed that many of the
typical problems you'll face in
distributed parallel systems can be
avoided by using this kind of
Linda-based architecture. Um, it um
it didn't really kind of pan out. Not
too many I don't know many systems that
use this approach. One um kind of
prominent um
implementation uh is JavaSpaces, which
is uh an implementation of this
technology um that's actually part of
Jini or Jini is built on top of this
one, I don't know.
No, I I think JavaSpaces evolved out of
Jini kind of.
Okay, this way. So, so but again,
there's not many systems that use it.
But but it's really an interesting
approach. And the what's interesting
from a patterns theory viewpoint um is
that the the the Java spaces in Linda
kind of thing is different from
Blackboard because although it uses the
same idea, the same solution, a common
repository where agents work with atomic
operations, it's certainly a different
pattern because the forces in the
problem are completely different. In the
Blackboard pattern originally, it's this
AI
worker algorithm non-deterministic
stuff, whereas in the other um
case, it's about concurrency and
atomicity and concurrency. So, different
patterns, very similar solution.
So, let's look at the consequences.
Yeah, um
having the the AI variant of it, so the
the original Blackboard, uh it's good
for experimentation for uh just fiddling
around with uh constellations of
responsibilities, how you could optimize
uh your solution, how you could create
new ways of finding a potential
solution. Um of course, the the the
separation of the individual um
responsibilities through the shared
repository, through the Blackboard, um
improves exchange exchangeability and
maintainability of the system. And uh
here the the the system is also this
this pattern is also very often used. It
it makes the system fault tolerant and
robust because well, yeah, the
individual responsibilities might fail,
but the data it might be still there if
replicated.
Right. That that's the point. This this
fault tolerance and robustness is of
course only relevant if it's a
distributed repository. So, processes or
or even machines can fail, whereas the
other workers are still there.
Uh as a consequence, it's of course uh
very difficult to test.
Uh you can imagine having the individual
responsibilities operate on the same
data and now track and trace and and
debug
what's going on. Well, it's a nightmare.
Um well, no optimal solution is
guaranteed. Well, it it just proceeds as
it as it goes and it it's
Just again, this AI stuff, you know.
Yeah.
The regarding the the efficiency, you
have when you have concurrent accesses
to the same data, you have transactions.
You need to really be careful not to
access the same data and and this might
slow out um
pace down your your system. So, you
might have a low efficiency here.
Yeah, and and and just to to to mention
this, it always sounds like we we we're
kind of making fun of artificial
artificial intelligence, but that's I
think that's not what we want to do. I
think AI has its has has its merits, but
it's certainly not the black ball
pattern that is, you know, that decides
about success and failure of AI. They
have completely different techniques and
different paradigms about which we might
talk in the future episodes. So, this
pattern is somewhat I don't know.
I would call it shared repository. Then
it works for me.
And forget about the AI stuff.
Yes.
Right.
Okay, microkernel. That's a pattern you
probably have all heard about because
Windows NT
and then some other operating systems um
are built on top of it.
So,
the idea is that
the microkernel pattern is useful for
systems that adapt to changing system
hardware, whatever, requirements. It
separates a minimal functional core from
extended functionality and customer
specific parts. The kernel also serves
as a socket for plugging in these
extensions and
and coordinate their collaboration. So,
in operating systems, you know this. You
have a very small kernel usually and
then you have drivers which are somewhat
privileged. They can work way near to
the kernel very efficiently and then you
have have the external services known as
applications in operating systems, which
are somewhat more somewhat further away
from the kernel itself. And of course,
if you have a
well layered architecture where the
microkernel is a very low layer. That's
another way to see it, I think. Um then
of course, changing the microkernel will
make sure that or porting the
microkernel to a different environment
will make sure that the rest of the
applications, which are based on top of
the microkernel, is still working. So,
Michael, um I don't know. Do Do you Do
you see this very different from from
from layers?
I I see it different because it has a
different focus. Where layers just help
me to structure my system into into your
layers of responsibility, this here
helps me to encapsulate a responsibility
even horizontally.
Um For example, in the remoting episode,
we discussed the the CORBA architecture
already. And so, when I have to talk
about a microkernel pattern, I I like to
refer to the CORBA architecture because
that for me implements
a typical microkernel. You have the orb
core with a minimal function
functionality to transport um a request
from A to B. And it doesn't care about
the data types. It doesn't care about
specific incarnations of whether you use
it for notifications, for events, for
for two-way invocations between A and B.
It just has a basic means of
transporting messages. And then you have
those extensions. You have those
plugins. For example, interceptors,
you have the proxies, you have the the
decoding part, you have the invoker, and
and
the marshaler, and those are all
extensions to the the orb core, uh which
made it
succeed for a certain while, and well,
we don't have to discuss
its situation today,
but for for that extent, it it was quite
successful and extensible to
to a certain extent, um
and the the orb core is the microkernel
in that case, and and the the the
further libraries are the extensions of
the microkernel.
Right. So, so, so,
again coming back, would you agree that
um
microkernel is layers, where the lowest
layers are made as
narrow
with as small an interface as possible?
Yeah,
yes, but also the horizontal effect, so
that the same level of abstraction I
would
factor
out and find the minimal point.
Okay.
Consequences, well, of course, it
improves the portability. Only the the
microkernel needs to be ported because
all the extensions then base on the
microkernel, on its API.
Um if in reality, if you change
the the operating system or things you
you have also
porting effort at that at the extension
level, but still the the key effort and
the the most effort should be spent at
the microkernel level only.
Um you have extensibility. Well, that is
all or that is the key what what you use
the microkernel pattern for,
to be extensible, to be flexible,
um and
yes, it it's it scales to an certain
extent to to a certain limits. And I
don't know how you could know in advance
um
where the limit is. Or I I often have
the feeling that a certain microkernel
architecture has its limits and and you
reach them at some some end. So, it's
scalable but with some limits when you
just extend it want to extend it with
things that it was not supposed to do in
advance.
One example, going back to the CORBA
example, was when really implementing
asynchronous
on on top of the inherently synchronous
communication in in the broker
architecture. I guess we get also to
broker then then later. Then here the
the it was really stretched the the the
the means.
Yeah, so because the core abstraction of
the microkernel was wrong. Or or not
supposed to perform the new kind
Yeah, was was not supposed to support
that initially.
As a further liability, the the
complexity
we should mention.
And here the point is that
designing the extensions on top of this
minimal set of of an API of the of the
microkernel can be quite cumbersome and
and grow complex for for doing well,
complicated things.
And also performance might suffer
because you have to work around some of
the minimalist operations provided by
the microkernel and and do weird stuff
because the abstractions provided by the
microkernel are not 100% fitting to what
you would would like to do.
Next one is the broker pattern.
We discussed the broker pattern in the
remoting episodes already in in large
detail. And but
let's discuss it in in its architectural
concept context. The outside view, the
impact of a broker uh, pattern in an
architecture. And here the broker helps
to connect previously
um,
um, distributed components to a new
um, system. And or or put it the other
way,
uh, it allows you to distribute your
components in a in a distributed
network, a distributed setting. And um,
in in current um,
um, development of projects, we learn
that uh, there is some uh, tight
coupling uh, involved when doing that.
And so the today uh, today we have a
trend to going to to publish subscribe
to messaging um,
architectures
where you don't have this tight coupling
where you don't have invocations at the
at a component or even object level as
you had previously or or originally with
the broker architectures, uh, but have a
loose coupling between the invocations.
I don't want to mention now uh, SOA and
and web services that they they
definitely go into that direction.
Yeah.
Um, so we won't discuss the broker any
further here because we did this in the
remoting episode, right? Yes. Okay.
As examples
uh, of course it's it's the same
candidates as we discussed in the in the
remoting episode. It's CORBA, .NET
remoting, Java RMI, DCOM.
Okay. The
next architectural style, this one I
think is not described in POSA as a
pattern, but doesn't matter. Still
allowed to talk about it. Um, the
workflow engine style the idea is
basically that you separate your
application logic into
typically stateless and rather primitive
services that provide a certain
functionality. And uh, on the other
hand, you describe some kind of
workflow,
for example, a state machine or an
activity diagram or a BPEL or a BPMN
diagram or whatever.
And the idea is that there is some kind
of workflow engine which executes the
workflow, and as part of the workflow,
the primitive services or actions are
called. Um so, if if you've listened to
SOA part one, the episode with
Eberhardt, then you will recognize that
service-oriented architecture is
basically an implementation of the
workflow engine architectural style
because, as Eberhardt said, one of the
really important characteristics of a
SOA is that you
explicitly describe the processes that
are happening in your in your
uh enterprise, I should say,
and
that these um
workflows or or processes that you
describe access
services in terms of SOA um to to
implement some of the side effects
basically as the process um proceeds.
So, um this is a very hot topic then,
probably, but nobody talks about it in
terms of workflow engine. It's it's it's
business process modeling and business
process whatever these days.
So, um
of course, known uses workflow systems.
That's the whole point of workflow
systems where you describe workflows
typically graphically, and then um they
can access like CORBA objects or web
services or whatever else as part of
their actions. And of course, as I said,
SOA is basically the same thing. Um
So, consequences. The workflow is easily
configurable. So, you typically have
your basic services
um
and you can easily compose them into
different
applications by just drawing or
otherwise modeling a different um
process.
Um you can also easily exchange the
activities. You don't have to touch the
process necessarily, and you can of
course reuse uh some of the basic um
um some of the basic services in
different
processes or workflows. So,
that's that's the whole idea, separating
out the process part of an application.
Um
and as I said, very very hyped these
days. Um negative, um
although you could argue whether really
negative, you have a very strict
application model. You you can't, you
know, implement it all kinds of use
cases because you have to restrict
yourself to
the idea of having services on the one
hand side and the workflow or the
process on the other hand side. Now, I
think this is actually an advantage
because you will only use uh this
architectural style for applications
which naturally can be um
like decomposed into services and the
process. And then this is a very natural
fit. And And again, this is the whole
idea behind uh using this pattern in
SOA. You have business processes in your
in your enterprise, and you really want
to represent them as a first-class
citizen and not as something that's
somewhere implemented in your
application code somehow.
The next style or technique that we want
to discuss are component architectures.
Component architectures or the component
container principle
um is very useful when you want to
separate, especially technical concerns
like security, persistence,
uh etc. Um
into uh
away from the application, away from the
component into a container. And when you
want to um
reuse those concerns, the infrastructure
there for for various applications.
Uh typical implementation
examples are EJB
or Com Plus or the
.NET framework
or micro components, right?
Corba components, but kind of dead, I
mean, to be honest.
Yeah, okay.
It It It was It used to be a good
example extending the EJB model, but now
I think just everybody does EJB.
Or Or Or even other things like Spring
or
some more lightweight
Yeah.
Although EJB 3.0, everything's good now.
The advantage of of course is that you
have hopefully reusable components that
if at all, only depend on the
technology. Now, today with EJB 3
and annotations, you depend less on the
infrastructure as previously
and
And of course, a primary idea is that
application developers don't have to
care about the technical concerns
because they're handled more or less
magically by the application server.
Yes, an important topic is also
concurrency. If you move the concurrency
into the the container,
you get a lot
of
hassle, a lot of um
risk into out of your project.
Yeah. And then again, this is a very a
very big topic on its own
and we'll probably have some kind of
episode on app application servers and
component containers later. So, we're
not going to discuss this in too much
detail.
Um
Uh
dinner is waiting, so we have to hurry
up.
The last thing I guess we want to
discuss um or also just mention because
it's something we should talk about in a
separate episode is frameworks.
Um and everybody knows what a framework
is, I guess. So, there are several
definitions. For example, one that I
read by Eric Gamma says, "A framework is
a set of cooperating classes which
together make up a reusable design for a
specific kind of software. A framework
provides an architectural guidance by
structuring the system in abstract
classes as well as the responsibilities
and interactions. The framework
developer framework user adapts the the
framework to his specific needs by
deriving concrete classes or by
assembling classes provided by the
framework." So, this is very very strict
definition. That's probably too narrow.
Other people say a framework is just the
Hollywood principle, "Don't call us, we
call you." So, you provide a couple of
callbacks and the framework calls into
these callbacks whenever it thinks is
necessary. So, there's one important
difference between a framework and and a
general-purpose library and that is
again that the callback idea. So, if you
if you use a library, it's up to you to
define the overall application flow, the
overall, you know, microscopic
application structure and you can use
fine-grained services provided by
libraries. In a framework, it's
different. The framework provides the
overall structure, the overall flow, the
overall metaphor for the application and
you just provide
details to the overall thing. For
example, if you have a drawing
application which can draw all kinds of
nice things, then you can extend this
application framework by new figures.
So, you provide an implementation of a
figure class, for example, and then the
overall drawing application can use this
figure
as if it had been there all the time.
So, that's different from from
libraries.
One important thing is that if you
define a framework, it's easy to get it
too generic. So, it, you know, there's
the danger that you might want to make
it handle all kinds of cases. So, the
framework's going to become big and very
very hard to use and you have to make
sure you avoid this. But again, this is
something for a separate episode.
There are other things that are
interesting to talk about
architecturally, for example, reflection
meta programming, plugins. But, again,
this is stuff for separate episodes.
We've taken the appropriate notes.
Um so, before we uh finish with this
episode, the question remains, now,
okay, we we have these we have these
architectural patterns, what role do
they play play in architecting a system?
How do you actually use them?
Well, as we uh briefly discussed at the
beginning of the episode,
um
you start off with a set of
responsibilities.
Um
for example, design using CRC cards,
class responsibility collaboration
cards, uh
initially
um
documented and uh not to say invented by
Ward Cunningham. You start off with
those
um responsibilities.
You have interactions between them. And
now you you you you list your
non-functional requirements and and skim
through in your mind through the
patterns that you know, through the
styles, and and apply it and and look at
it and and
at that moment um
assess how the result would be, what
what kind of consequences you would
have, uh how
how you would actually fulfill now
applying this pattern in this situation
the the the the the non-functional
requirements. And um
after a while doing that, it it's then
just a gut feeling. You You hear about a
set of responsibilities, you hear about
some constraints, and you initially uh
point on one of the styles, on one of
the patterns, and it becomes pretty easy
pretty soon A gut feeling that you apply
and it's
the one of the
tool kits of of an architect
applying those styles
with wisdom, not everywhere where it
fits.
It's it's of use and and benefit of the
project. So,
when having decided for an architectural
style, do some discussion,
document it, have it reviewed by others
to get their opinion
whether this architectural style really
resolved all your forces that that you
are faced in in in your project and in
your specific context.
So, I'd like to add one one or two of
five sentences to that. One is that I
think usually architectural styles
aren't used
literally. So, they serve as a kind of
stepping stone when finding your
solution, your architectural solution.
So, so if you
if you picture your architectural design
space as a three three-dimensional space
and you start, you know, at the origin
and you wander around and try to find
the right spot where you you know, where
all your forces are balanced and where
your your architectural has a has a nice
implementation, nice structure, then the
design the architectural patterns are
like certain points in in this three or
whatever dimensional space and you
wander around and you get, you know, you
get near a certain architectural style
and you basically you you gravitate to
that style and you say, "Okay, now I
have the pipes and filters pattern.
Let's see whether this fits." And then
you might say, "Oh, no, it doesn't fit."
So, you go on wandering around again.
You kind of gravitate to a different
pattern and then you think, "Oh, yeah,
that might fit." And then you evaluate
the forces and see how much you have to
tweak it so that it actually fit fits
your problem.
Okay.
I think that's it for this episode. As
we said before, dinner is waiting. We
have to stop. So, thanks for listening
and um
bye-bye. See you next time.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about engineering radio
or if you want to give us feedback,
please go to our website at
SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although, we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauly for the intro and outro music as
well as Lipson for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE-Radio as well as all
other episodes is licensed under
Creative Commons license. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.